place
where I was ready to take calculus and I
also came back to uh higher education as
a non-traditional student after about
four or five years away from high school
after I worked as a journalist for a few
years so I I I say all this to say that
when people think of people who are good
at math they might think of someone who
did like a who was in math contests
or could calculate things quickly and I
was not any of those I would say that
one of the things I do well is working
with mental models of things and looking
at some different mental models of math
has helped me a lot there are two mental
models that I always find helpful to
share at the outset the first is called
the rule of four which is a way of
thinking about how we represent
mathematical
Concepts and it's not just four it it
could be more than four but the idea
behind the rule of four which to my
knowledge um was originated
by uh Deborah Hughes Hallet and her
co-authors in one of their calculus
books is that there are multiple ways to
represent mathematical
ideas which are usually set up as
graphs numbers words and symbols and
that the more of these you can use and
Link together the greater likelihood you
have of making your ideas understood and
also I would say of effectively solving
problems
later so for the sake
of efficiency lots of times things are
highly symbolic and highly compressed
but the more we can decompress kind of
unzip those equations
and expand them out into
experiential understanding and multiple
representations that usually seems to
add a lot of value to people's
experience with
math and one of the most destructive
things that sometimes happens to people
is they are pressured to compute
quickly in a way that makes their
selfworth seem as if it is at risk if
they cannot do so and is usually what
turns people off from
math most people can remember the moment
where they or I would say many people
can remember the moment where they
stopped liking math and so if we can
just go back to before that time and
work around it it seems to work pretty
well the other major concept that I like
to use which is not mass
specific is well let me stop there is
there anything y'all have any thoughts
on
that I agree with uh a lot of people get
turned off of math based on personal
experiences maybe with an instructor or
just hitting a wall with a Concepts or
not being fast enough things like that I
can recall so many kids in school who
are like very intelligent but then they
had a subject like it was math or
chemistry and then the way the
instructor taught and their reaction to
their
struggles just turn them off from the
subject
completely and we don't have to do that
that's like the we're not on that path
that has an objective like a traditional
school is so we can look at all the
different ways we could approach this
terrain
and each find our own part of it and how
we Traverse it which is what's so
exciting to me about being a
mathematician and a pedagogist professor
whatever outside of that setting where
it's in a linear objective oriented
way the other cognitive tool that I
really find valuable as a high level
thing is not math specific but it is
about teaching but it's not it's useful
in lots of other contexts outside of
teaching this this idea of blooms
taxonomy this is U something I used
quite a bit when I was making exams or
projects thinking about
assessments that there are different
levels of doing things and the types of
things like using the multiplication
table or taking a derivative is at the
lowest level of understanding which is
not to say that it's not important the
lowest level can be
foundational but it's not all there
is I co-author I know I did not
co-author let me speak accurately
um I in toward a student who wrote an
article about chain Rule and she was an
artist so she was creating these images
that were giving this very intuitive
easy to understand way of working on
this calculus
concept
and it was totally at the high level
that is not hey can you apply this but
it was about creating
something that led to deeper
understanding or more
insight we don't have to go from the
bottom up and we don't have to
go we there's no specific entry point
that you have to come at this from so if
I were teaching this as my class which I
am not I might ask students to create
things well before they felt like they
really understood them because you can
do that uh you could ask someone just
create an equation any equation make it
as complex as you want and they don't
necessarily have
to be coming in with a a background of
lots of practice before they do that but
when I put these two things together
what I get is an emphasis on multiple
representations and multiple approaches
that you have different representation
systems
verbal visual graphical numerical
symbolic and you have multiple levels at
which you can approach the activities
and when you put that together there's
just tons of different things you can do
RJ I see you have your hand up please
feel free to jump
in I was just going to say on the um I I
had done some work a long time ago uh in
education technology and uh some of it
was on
um uh uh repetition based learning and
that move you know that move from okay
we're g to just get this as a rope you
know you can remember this thing to
actually understanding it uh uh there's
something called The Generation effect
which is is like you contributing to
your model of the thing right that is
like uh uh you know uh trying to
visually represent the idea creating
anything rather than just consuming uh
it's it's it's you know like they call
it generation effect because has this
this really really significant impact on
on retention so even if you w trying to
uh build on the thing but uh uh you know
just just trying to um represent it in a
different way has like this C crazy
impact on your on your understanding of
it and that I it's a um I think it's I
think it's like the explanation for why
it is like physical note-taking um has a
a greater impact than um say like
listening to a recorded lecture like you
know you recorded the lecture in class
and then afterward you listen to it it's
very different from uh uh in terms of
retention impact than than writing the
notes as you go along um so it's kind of
it's interesting because like you know
taxonomy represented is like this linear
up and down but you can kind of like go
from jump to create and then come back
down to evaluate and analyze anyway it's
just it made me think of that
yeah I really like that and I mean it's
how often are people able to apply
things before they understand them and
they understand them through app
right it's it's not like you have to
jump in at one specific place and go up
or down it's that there are multiple
different things you can do so I kind of
think of these like a pyramid I put the
rule of four at the base uh and then I I
stack these sliced triangles on top of
it and uh end up with a mental model of
a mental model of a cognitive space that
you can navigate as a way of working
with
mathematics and so that might be helpful
context for anyone watching this or
coming to these meetings to understand
why we're it might feel like we're
jumping around but we're trying to map
in lots of different ways and create
connections between these different
things I hope that makes
sense
and that might give some context for
looking at so what I did in anticipation
of this
meeting um because I am not I would not
claim the title of expert about active
inference I've been familiar with
it uh for about no I've been exposed to
it for a little over a year but I'm just
now getting to a place where I have time
to really focus on it so I'm reading the
textbook for the first
time and what I did was look through
the chapter
two and through the appendices to
see what might be um
helpful so maybe some of these things
with a little bit of
priming when we see them if you haven't
totally fine if you haven't read them
yet um RJ knows I like a
very improvisational
person so when I was asked what should
we do before tomorrow and was thinking
that's a really it'd be great if I
thought about that wouldn't it um the
first thing I'm going to try to do is
find the textbook which I
think I found a moment
ago but what I did was I went through
the
chapter two and the
appendices to see both what the
recommended mathematical background is
and what the
um what is coming up like next week in
terms of what we might be exposed
to so I thought we could walk through
that a little bit with a particular
emphasis
on not
here it is not the active inference per
se but what ideas are we going to see
and what what do this ideas mean and um
how might we be somewhat familiar with
them so what I saw in chapter 2
just to reality check myself chapter 2
is the next thing that the group looks
at
right or is it two chapters per or two
weeks per chapter
it's it's if someone is able to check
that would be great if not
super it's not it's not a
blocker
um anyway let's let's talk about this
which is the first math equation that
pops up in
the in the
textbook and it's two fundamental rules
of
probability because probability is very
important in this chapter as we talk
about what is the certainty or the
likelihood that something is true given
the available evidence that we
have so this first rule of
probability quickly
um
to review what I always start with if I
teach probability from
foundations is probability is a way of
assigning numbers to things that could
happen that give us an intuitive sense
of How likely or unlikely something is
and probably anyone who comes to this
these
sessions has at least some intuitive
idea of probability even if whether or
not there's a formal
definition and many people also have
formal
definitions um this first rule the sum
of all events
probability sum of the probability of
all events has to equal one tells
us something has to
happen and this concept the name for
this is the suu
um
think but something has to happen so we
have a probability
space and we can divide that probability
space which is everything that could
happen we can divide that into
events and then each event has a
probability and if you take each of
those distinct events and add them
up it has to be one has to be 100%
because something has to
happen the other key observation that
you can build off of is What's called
the product
rule um the notation there's a lot of
different types of notation that pop up
here so
this
probability of X comma
Y is
called The Joint
distribution and this is the or the
joint probability excuse me and this is
the probability that both X and Y
happen you will see other notation for
this this could also be the probability
of X and Y some people like to use words
instead of the
comma um or you might also see this as
the probability some
older texts use
a symbol that looks
like
this and I just realized how awful that
looks when I type directly on white so
I'm going to move this over here
so there's the joint probability which
is the probability that we're interested
in two things and that this is the
probability both of them
happen there's the marginal probability
which is the probability of one single
event happen
and there's the conditional
probability so the marginal probability
is just the probability of a single
event The Joint probability is the
probability of what's sometimes called a
compound event where two things are
happening and then there's the
conditional probability which is the
probability
that something happens given a specific
piece of
[Music]
information when you see p of XY or P of
X or P of Y with this divider between it
this is pronounced
probability of Y given X which means I
already know for sure that X has
happened and it's not hard for us to
think
of specific cases where if I know
something has happened it drastically
changes my
probability uh
of something else
happened so these are the three
different types of probability that show
up in these rules I think it's worth
talking about them because especially
for people who aren't as you know deep
in this you're going to hear these three
different adjectives and it's good to
recognize which is
which the other thing is we're looking
at this from aasan perspective which
means we think of probabilities as
corresponding to
beliefs so probability is not a fact
about the
universe a probability is a belief that
we hold and that's sort of the
justification for why if I know an
additional piece of
information it can
change my belief about the probability
of another piece of information being
true I said a lot there and I'm not I
don't want to lecture the entire time
but does what I've said make sense
here I think these are three concept
steps worth
highlighting cool so we can look at
resources about the difference between
those
things and from here there's these
Basics when I say basic I'm not saying
easy I'm saying fundamental
these different ideas
about what you can do with these from
here you can
build product rule the way that product
rule and sum rule play together which is
marginalization and you can also build
various forms of Base
rule
so if you look up base rule on Wikipedia
which we might as well do you it'll look
different ways there are different forms
that can be written in they all have the
same
justification what I really like about
probability is unlike
calculus the you can start with the few
fundamental axioms of
probability and really develop it in a
logical way without needing too much
time too much space
so just starting with the two rules the
product rule and the sum rule you can
get to this uh base
theorem which tells you a relationship
between two different conditional
probabilities and two different marginal
probabilities already here you'll see
the difference in
notation um
for compound
events like
this definition of conditional
probability is what the book is
[Music]
calling product rule and already there's
they're using the the intersection sign
instead of the
[Music]
comma
um how is this useful so I mean there's
the formula you can practice using the
formula you can look at the visual proof
or intuition about what it
means how is this useful this is
useful the the classic example is about
testing for a
disease
so the classic example here would be
that you take a test for
let's say cancer it's a popular example
and it comes back
positive you know the the false positive
rate there is a false positive rate so
you know the the false positive and
false negative rates of the
tests what is the probability that you
actually do have cancer
given that the test came back
positive this is a classic example of
how to apply beige
rule um I'm sure I can find an example
online where they go through it in
detail and this is the type of
calculation that shows up several times
in this chapter at least
conceptually where we observe something
which should be the test being positive
and then we want to update our
information about the likelihood of
something which would be the
disease the way that this occurs
is um so that's the big picture idea
of what this uh box is getting
at and why it might be useful
there's this terminology of Prior and
likelihood and I like this example in
the book of trying to determine whether
you have an apple or a
frog the prior here is the the prior
belief that you have
before you you know you get additional
information so the prior would be before
you take the T T How likely you think it
is that you have the
disease and
then the likelihood
model is something it would be about the
test it would be what you know about the
relationship between the test results
and actually having the disease
and I think the the book does a fairly
good job of illustrating this maybe it
would be worth us doing some exercises
or something at some point but just for
this high level overview that we're
looking at and trying to maybe make it
more comfortable let's skip like
calculations I I'll give you homework if
you want it but I don't want to just
start there
and all of these calculations are using
the rules in the box so being familiar
with the rules in the Box are helpful to
understand where these numbers actually
come
from the explanation is is great
um then there's a
notion of
surprise surprise I I wasn't familiar
with this unit but after I read about it
it makes sense gats are like
bits they're the sort of continuous
version of bits bits measure how much
information bits are a measurement of
information that are expressed base two
if if you if you're familiar all with
that because either zero or
one the discret binary and Nats are the
analog they're just working base e so
Nats are a different way of measuring
how much information you get from
something interesting I I I did not know
that term gats and I feel like it's in
in deep memory somewhere where where
does that come from it comes from
natural log oh okay I see all right and
the same way that bit comes from U
binary
right um and the thing about is if
you're working with A continuous
probability distribution even if you're
not um in like statistical
thermodynamics there's
uncertainty and it it may make more
sense on some of the physical things to
measure information in a continuous way
and so the natur the natat actually
plays a role analogous to the bit and
you can convert between bits and NS just
like you can convert between me meters
and feet right they're just different
units so gats are how you measure
surprise and surprise is how much
information you get from a specific
observation and kind of a good place for
us to wrap up is where do we get to
like where we get to is that different
probability
models different probability
distributions will have
different different surprise statistics
Associated
to
and okay let me let me back up I I'm
there's a there's a common mistake here
and I thought I would go ahead and make
it actually a few different Notions of
surprise that that measure different
things and it's important to be careful
about that
uh so one thing I
should so using it's important to unpack
two different Notions of surprise the
first is
the negative law
evidence I don't want to get caught up
in the details here but the idea is the
this notion of surprise tells you how
unlikely something is and there's a
second notion called beian surprise
which is actually about updating uh
based on
beliefs so in other words beian surprise
quantifies the difference between a
prior what we what we think How likely
we think something is before we see
and a posterior How likely we think
something is after it actually happens
and what that leads into is like the big
math
question which is if you wanted to
quantify and say this probability
distribution is like this one or it is
not how would you do
that and it turns out there are lots of
different ways to do
that and one of them is the cack liebler
Divergence but the big picture on all of
these things because I'm not going to
have time to go deep in the details and
and we it's not the purpose of this
session anyway what all of these tools
are
doing is trying to give measurement to
information and measurement to
likelihood of of something
happening or something being
true and the symbols and everything else
are just reporting that and giving
concrete ways to calculate
it and we can go deeper in the weeds if
people want
to but when we talk about these things
we're talking about
information and how much confidence we
have something is true and what this
does is give us tools to measure
that
cool so let's continue this in Discord
I'm happy to continue it um but I need
to stop the sync session now what I will
say is I'm happy to give you homework if
you want it if people want to get their